<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../Common/Overview.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<VSSDKSample>
  <ImagePath>../../../Common</ImagePath>
  <Status>
    <Accessibility>true</Accessibility>
    <Comments>true</Comments>
    <Documentation>true</Documentation>
    <ErrorHandling>true</ErrorHandling>
    <FollowSDKCodingStandards>true</FollowSDKCodingStandards>
    <Localizable>true</Localizable>
    <Overview>true</Overview>
    <ScenarioTests>false</ScenarioTests>
    <Supported>true</Supported>
    <Style>Example</Style>
  </Status>
  <Overview>
    <ShortName>C# Example.IronPythonConsoleWindow</ShortName>
    <LongName>IronPython Console Window Integration</LongName>
    <Phrase>Integrating in Visual Studio a console window for IronPython.</Phrase>
  </Overview>
  <Introduction>
    <Summary>
      This sample is a component of IronPython integration inside Visual Studio.
      This sample defines a Visual Studio Package (VSPackage) that is responsible for the direct interaction with the IronPython engine. This 
      interaction can be expressed in two ways: handling the instances of the engine and running interactive commands against a 
      specific instance of the engine. The main goals of this sample are:
    </Summary>
    <Goal>Creating a Visual Studio service to generate new instances of the IronPython engine or get a reference to the instance of the engine used by the interactive console.</Goal>
    <Goal>Creating a tool window that implements the IronPython interactive console.</Goal>
    <Goal>Enabling statement completion inside the console window.</Goal>
    <Image width="400" height="400">ConsoleWindow.jpg</Image>
  </Introduction>
  <SampleInfo>
    <State>
    </State>
    <Type>Example</Type>
    <Complexity>2</Complexity>
    <Screenshot>ConsoleWindow.jpg</Screenshot>
    <Area>Iron Python</Area>
    <Language>C#</Language>
    <Folder>VisualStudioIntegration\Samples\IronPythonIntegration\</Folder>
    <SampleSolution>ConsoleWindow\ConsoleWindow.sln</SampleSolution>
    <Doc />
    <Keywords>
      <Keyword>Iron Python</Keyword>
      <Keyword>Console Window</Keyword>
      <Keyword>MSBuild Tasks</Keyword>
      <Keyword>engine</Keyword>
      <Keyword>Python</Keyword>
      <Keyword>interactive</Keyword>
      <Keyword>command</Keyword>
      <Keyword>console</Keyword>
    </Keywords>
  </SampleInfo>
  <GettingStarted>
    <Paragraph>
      The current version of this sample implements the Visual Studio service that exposes instances of
      the engine and a console window that allows the user to enter some text and execute it using the
      IronPython engine. This console also hosts the IronPython language service so that colorization
      and statement completion are available when typing commands.
    </Paragraph>
    <Paragraph>
      To expose the IronPython engine, we use two interfaces. The first interface is called
      IPythonEngineProvider and is used to create and register the service with the shell. The second
      interface is called IEngine and is an abstraction over the functionalities exposed by the engine.
      The IEngine interface is not required, but having its abstraction layer makes testing the package easier
      and help to isolate the console's code from changes in the engine.
    </Paragraph>
    <Paragraph>
      The definitions of these interfaces are contained in the IronPythonInterface.Dll assembly that is
      built from the Interfaces project.
    </Paragraph>
    <Paragraph>
      The console window is a tool window that creates a TextBuffer object and hosts a TextView
      control that is initialized to use the text buffer. This tool window derives from WindowPane
      to allow the base classes provided by the Managed Package Framework (MPF) to handle its creation and persistence,
      but it overrides the implementation of IVsWindowPane in order to use the one provided by the
      TextView object.
    </Paragraph>
    <Paragraph>
      The interaction between the console window and the IronPython engine is handled by the CommandBuffer
      class defined in file CommandBuffer.cs. This class handle aspects of the interaction like find out
      when the text entered by the user is ready to be executed, its execution or building the full text
      to execute in case of multi-line statement. The console window is responsible to intercept the ENTER
      key and add the text to the command buffer (see the OnReturn event handler in ConsoleWindow.cs).
    </Paragraph>
    <Paragraph>
      The console window also needs to check context when the user presses a key. For instance, the ENTER key should execute the command entered by
      the user, not add a new line to the buffer. Similarly, the UP ARROW and DOWN ARROW keys should show the previous
      and next commands in the command history, not move the cursor up and down.
      All these special keys are handled as specific commands by the shell, so the console window registers
      itself as a command filter with the text view and intercepts the commands that it needs to handle. You
      can see how the command filter is initialized by looking at the OnToolWindowCreated method in
      ConsoleWindow.cs.
    </Paragraph>
    <Paragraph>
      The history is implemented using a class called HistoryBuffer that stores the list of
      commands executed inside the console, sorted by execution order. When the user presses the UP ARROW or
      DOWN ARROW key, the console asks the history buffer for the previous or next element in the history and
      shows it in the text view.
    </Paragraph>
    <Paragraph>
      Statement completion and colorization are implemented using the same IronPython language service
      that is used inside the standard editor when editing a py file. Nevertheless, inside the console window,
      the language service will use a different way to build the list of methods used for the completion functionalities.
      The main difference between the behavior of the language service inside the console window and
      inside an editor window is that in the editor it will use static analysis of the text to
      build the list of the method in a class (the window that you can see when you type the dot key),
      while in the console it will use the engine to evaluate the current value of the variable.
    </Paragraph>
    <Paragraph>
      The different behavior of the language service in the editor window and console window is implemented
      using one functionality exposed by the IronPython language service through its version of the Source class.
      This object, defined in the MPF, is an abstraction on top of the text buffer and text view. The IronPython version
      of this class derives from the one provided by the framework and adds to it the ability to provide
      a custom AuthoringScope so that it will be used during the parsing of the text inside a specific
      view.
      The code that creates the text view inside ConsoleWindow.cs creates a PythonSource object for the
      language service associated to this view, sets the callback to create a custom AuthoringScope
      (called ConsoleAuthoringScope and implemented in ConsoleAuthoringScope.cs), and adds this to
      the list of special views for the language. At this point, everything is set to let the language
      service use two different kinds of scope during the parsing of the text.
    </Paragraph>
  </GettingStarted>
  <BuildingTheSample>
    <Step>
      Open the ConsoleWindow.sln solution.
    </Step>
    <Step>
      Press F5 to build the sample, register it in the experimental hive, and launch Visual Studio from the experimental hive.
    </Step>
  </BuildingTheSample>
  <RunningTheSample>
    <SampleTask>
      <Description>
        To see the sample's functionality...
      </Description>
      <Step>
        On the <bold>View</bold> menu, click <bold>Other Windows</bold>, and then click <bold>IronPython Console</bold>
        to display the console window.
      </Step>
      <Step>
        Type <bold>2+2</bold> and then press ENTER to see the sum.
      </Step>
      <Step>
        Type <bold>print "Hello"</bold> and press ENTER to see "Hello". 
        Notice that the keyword <bold>print</bold> and the string "Hello" are both colorized.
      </Step>
      <Step>
        Press the UP ARROW and DOWN ARROW keys to run through the command history.
      </Step>
    </SampleTask>
  </RunningTheSample>
  <AdditionalResources>
    <Resource>
      <Title>Visual Studio SDK Website</Title>
      <URL>http://msdn.microsoft.com/vstudio/extend</URL>
    </Resource>
  </AdditionalResources>
  <FunctionalTests>
  </FunctionalTests>
  <ProjectFiles>
    <File>
      <Name>IronPythonConsolePackage.cs</Name>
      <Description>
        This file contains the definition of the package. Inside this file is the code to register
        the service with the shell, with a registration attribute to update the registry and with a call
        to the base class's implementation of IServiceContainer to add the service to the list of the
        proffered services.
      </Description>
    </File>
    <File>
      <Name>IronPythonEngineProvider.cs</Name>
      <Description>
        This file contains the definition of the interface used to expose the service and the definition
        of the class that implements this interface in order to provide the actual implementation of the
        service.
      </Description>
    </File>
    <File>
      <Name>CommandBuffer.cs</Name>
      <Description>
        This file contains the implementation of the CommandBuffer class. This is the class that interacts
        with the IronPython engine to execute the text entered by the user.
      </Description>
    </File>
    <File>
      <Name>ConsoleWindow.cs</Name>
      <Description>
        This file contains the implementation of the console tool window. Here is where the text buffer,
        the text view, and the window frame are created, where the IronPython engine is initialized, and
        where the command handlers for the console are defined.
      </Description>
    </File>
    <File>
      <Name>ConsoleAuthoringScope.cs</Name>
      <Description>
        This file contains the implementation of the AuthoringScope used by the IronPython language 
        service when running inside the console window. The AuthoringScope is the object responsible
        for the creation of the list of methods shown by the statement completion window.
      </Description>
    </File>
    <File>
      <Name>HistoryBuffer.cs</Name>
      <Description>
        This is the implementation of a buffer specialized to store the history of the commands executed
        in the console window.
      </Description>
    </File>
    <File>
      <Name>TextBufferStream.cs</Name>
      <Description>
        Implementation of a class derived from System.IO.Stream that creates a stream on top
        of a text buffer. This is used by the console window to set the standard input and standard
        output streams of the IronPython engine.
      </Description>
    </File>
  </ProjectFiles>
</VSSDKSample>